hello and welcome to developmental
psychology we're going to start right
away with chapter one and work our way
through now chapter one is going to be a
little different than rest of the
chapters what we're going to be looking
at in this chapter is sort of an
overview of human development and the
study of human development when we get
into the later chapters um starting with
sort of chapter three we're really going
to start hitting different
ages so we want to start with a basic
definition of human development and what
we're talking about here in this class
is we're going to be looking at how
people change over a period of time as
we think about it who we were when we
were five versus who we were when we 10
15 20 25 and multiple ages after that
really changes and so this looks at
those changes we're going to look at
some physiological changes some
psychological changes but basically it's
going to be looking at the change now
this is not based on just one particular
area of science human development this
is going to be looking at multiple areas
so it's not just psychology but it'll be
physiology and social Concepts so
there's going to be a lot to do within
this
class now there are going to be three
themes that we keep talking about and
the first one is going to be nature
versus nurture so the question is is how
much who am I based on my genes that I
got from my parents and who who am I
based on the environment and this is is
something that's always a controversy
between the two how much does each one
give so is your IQ because of your
parents or is your IQ because you were
able to go to special schools and got
all kinds of special treatment and um
you know got high IQ things which one
really influenced your IQ the most and
we know that there's going to be some
that's based on your environment and
there's going to be some that's going to
be based on your genetics and we'll be
looking at that now continuity versus
discontinuity basically is this a smooth
smoth pass or do we have stages now this
one's pretty easy to spot when you talk
about things because if we talk about
stages so we'll talk about a gentleman
named Eric Ericson later on and we talk
about his stages of development which
means he sees this as discon
continuality which means is not smooth
and keep going whereas our physical
development we can think of that as sort
of continuality that there's not really
a stop and start sort of to that process
when we're talking about babies
growing now Universal versus context
specific development the question is is
is there only one way to develop or does
our society and our environments and
where we grow does that affect the way
that we develop and so your book gives a
really good example about how the
children in the United States don't
learn to count money until they're you
know somewhere in the second or third
grade is when we really begin to work on
money and yet there are kids in other
parts of the world which are counting
money very early in life um many of them
are doing money and stuff like this by
time they're five or or six they're down
in the marketplac is selling basic
things so that kind of shows us that
learning to count money is not a
universal thing it doesn't happen all
the same time around the world it's
rather a context specific
thing the forces that we'll be talking
about that tends to make up this subject
is first our biological forces so that's
our genetics and health related things
we'll talk about the psychological
forces within development and cognitive
is one of the things we talk about the
most now cognitive is a word that
sometimes people hear sometimes don't
hear but let's make sure we're all on
the same page for this definition
cognitive is thinking some of you might
think of it as the mind when we say
what's the study of psychology and
people say the study of the Mind really
they're talking about how we think how
we problem solve how we do things and
that's sort of where cognitive sits our
social cultural forces are something we
also focus on so the question is is how
does our society our ethic eity and our
interpersonal Rea reactions to things
really help develop who we are as a
person and who we are across um cultures
and even us for ourselves so I live here
on the beach and does living on the
beach give me a different sort of social
cultural background the people who live
on the mainland we always call us beach
bums and those are the mainlanders and
there is s slight differences and it
does affect who we become as people and
then we have to think about life forces
and those what we're talking about here
is that our our life cycle this life
cycle forces tend to also dictate who we
are there are only certain times in our
life that certain things are going to
happen and so those life cycle forces
then affect who we become as people and
who we are at the
moment now the first thing is we're
going to talk about what is a theory
theory is one of those words that tends
to be thrown around a lot and we use a
very specific uh definition within
psychology basically it's an organized
set of ideas as designed to explain some
sort of development basically a theory
has to be something that has gone
through some sort of scientific analysis
and it's done through experimentation or
scientific study of some sort and we'll
talk a lot about scientific studies
later on but a theory is not something
that comes from the gut now we do hear
people use words that way however that
truly is a hypothesis because we are in
a science class now so we're not going
to use Theory as a guess a theory has to
be something that has been
proven we're going to be covering a
bunch of different areas within
psychology and these are sort of some of
the biggies you might want to say um
psychoanalysis here we're going to be
talking about Freud and Ericson now
Ericson's really going to be your big
person for this class in fact you're
going to need Ericson for the rest of
your time if you were going into the
nursing foundations um nursing very much
focuses on Ericson and so I warn the
nurses you need to be able to memorize
and regurgitate Ericson Skinner is going
to come under our Learners and some of
you may have heard about Skinner back in
your intro class and Operate
conditioning when we talk about
cognitive it's all about p p as our big
guy and we will talk about Mr V over
here um he's a little bit more in the
cognitive area we don't focus on him as
much and then finally we have our
ecological and I simply call him Yuri
because I say his name wrong all the
time and those are going to be our big
ones we're going to focus on now when we
get into the chapters we're going to get
into these gentlemen a little bit more
specifically and their theories of human
development specifically this one we're
just going to kind of skim over a little
bit about many of
them so when we talk about Freud one of
the things we like about Freud is that
he really brings um psychology into the
academic world until Freud comes along
we mostly had psychology in the
background it was something we just did
with crazy people in institutions or it
was mostly only done within Academia but
he says hey you know what there are
other people who really need to use
psychology and we need to use psychology
in multiple ways so he brings this out
sort of to the real world which is why
Freud is so well known he also brought a
lot of the words that we tend to use
today anal personality librito denial
these are all words that come basically
from Freud in fact the word ego is
developed by Freud now Freud also
develops this concept that there are
three parts of the mind and if you took
our intro class you kind of cover this a
little bit but we've got the conscious
the preconscious and the unconscious now
the conscious is what you're aware of so
right now you are listening to me which
means that your conscious is working um
preconscious may be things that you're
aware of but you're not really focused
on right now but if you focus on it you
would understand it now the unconscious
is sort of our biological instincts
these are the things that sort of sit
underneath the surface and we're not
always aware of it he truly felt that if
we could become more aware of our
unconscious area that we would be able
to have better control of it and that
was the goal that he was working on was
the goal of
control if we look at his three parts of
personality and again this is just a
quick review from our intro class what
we have is the conscious the
preconscious and the unconscious but
within those three parts of Personality
we have the ID the ego and the super ego
now remember the ID is all about
pleasure it's sort of the the Pleasure
Principle it rules you as far as wanting
to have fun but what's interesting is is
that it's in the unconscious so
generally he felt like this drive to
have pleasure was something we weren't
always aware we controlling us so my
great example always is this morning
when you woke up there was this little
voice that said just stay in bed bed is
good don't get up well you can think of
that as your ID you probably weren't
really aware that it was saying that to
you and he thought was is that if you
were somebody who were too focused on
Pleasure too much trying to always have
fun all the time then we needed to help
you focus on how to listen to that voice
and control that voice well that voice
is controlled by the ego which you
notice is in the conscious and the pre-
unconscious and a little bit in the
unconscious area basically he really
thought the ego was is very complex
thing but it was ruled by the reality
principle it's that little voice that
this morning that said no get your ass
out of bed and move so your ego is the
one that sort of manages your day-to-day
activities he thought if your ID was too
big that basically your ego got squished
so you were basically running around
looking for fun all the time without
really thinking about the reality of
what that might do to you so you think
about the friends you know who are
always sort of in trouble because all
they do is run around and have fun and
they don't think about the financial
cost or the physical cost this might
have and he would say they're being
ruled by their ID where in the other
thing is is that we would have the ego
and if the ego was too big it covered up
sort of the ID and people stopped having
fun all they did was work all they did
was try to manage things um they became
very controlling and because that's what
they needed to do was control their
world all the time so he always was
looking for this sort of balance between
the ID and the ego then the last thing
is he had this super ego and the super
ego is kind of interesting he said the
super ego go really where our values and
our morals SAT but it's the place that
really we judge things so we judge the
actions that we took not the actions of
others but the actions that we took
ourselves and he really felt that if you
were taking an action that was not
within what you thought was correct then
that tended to build anxiety or if you
didn't know what action to take that
would build anxiety I need a couple of
different anxieties we're not so
interested in that in this class but you
notice that the super ego runs sort of
the length of the ID and the ego and
that's because he really felt that it
had a very strong component to what we
do also notice that if you look at this
little line where the unconscious is
that most of it actually sits in our
unconscious and he really felt that a
lot of what drove us we just weren't
aware of and that's why he really
focused on trying to make people more
aware of their
actions now Ericson he actually studies
under Freud he's what we call a Neo
and he really believed that culture was
sort of at the center of what we do it's
not that he didn't like um what Freud
said but he kind of just took it another
step now we're going to be covering
Ericson a great deal when we get into
each um phase of life and so the thing
is is that he has these eight stages um
that
all develop who we are now we thought
most of them happened before we were 18
um but the the development itself really
varied on what he called these crisises
so here are the basic stages don't worry
about memorizing regurgitating them now
as I said we're going to go into these
in more depth when we get into each
chapter but what we have are these basic
conflicts so when we're young from birth
to 18 months of old he really felt like
this trust or mistrust was what we were
working on and then we had the anatomy
autonomy versus shame and doubt you know
did we get to find that we walked and
talked ourselves or were we always
worried about what somebody else was
saying then somewhere in preschool the
question is is did we begin to take
initiative or we always feeling guilty
about you know trying to move forward
you might want to say um he thought in
school industrious versus inferiority
becomes in there basically we need to
begin to able to cope with things we
need to be able to develop a sense of
ourselves away from our parents and we
also need to be able to figure out if
we're going to do things for ourselves
or we just always going to wait for
somebody else to do it adolesence is one
of our fun stages we have a couple of
chapters dedicated to just adolescence
and the big thing in adolescence is
beginning to identify who we are and
developing that identity and that causes
a lot of strife you might want to say in
one's life because we have to begin to
decide how much of what we decide Is Us
and how much of what we decide is based
on our parents even down to things like
the shampoo we use is it my am I using
the shampoo because I picked it or
because my parents picked it for me
basically who am I as a person and
there's a lot of conflict at this time
as far as internally trying to figure
out who I am in young adulthood it knows
he says 19 to 40 but this happens a
little bit more like in the 20s and the
30s we're talking about intimacy versus
isolation basically are we going to be
able to develop longlasting loving
relationships now these relationships
don't always have to be of a sexual
nature we're talking about friendships
we're talking about you know good
friends that we might be able to do or
are we going to wind up in isolation
where we don't have a whole lot of
friends now he believes that a lot of
this has to also deal with identity that
if we haven't developed our identity
it's really going to be hard for us to
develop
intimacy now um this phase when we're
talking about our older middle youth
kind of adulthood basically up till
retirement age is talking about are we
going to be keep moving forward are we
going to stagnate are we just going to
be you know we hit 40 and we just don't
really change much until we retire and
he really felt that the people who kept
moving and progressing and doing things
and finding new things were people who
tended to be happier versus the people
who went into stagnation where they just
really didn't do much new things um then
at the end when we talk about 65 to
death and yeah we might actually bump
that up a little bit higher um the
question is is are we happy with the
life we've chosen or do we tend to go
into Despair and again we're going to
cover each one of these much more in
depth when we go to each chapter this is
the only time though in your chapter
you're going to see all of them together
so if you're a person who every once in
a while wants to go back and say wait a
minute I I forgotten how this one
relates to that one mark this page in
your book and you'll want to go back and
look at it the chart of the book looks a
little bit different than this one I
kind of like this one um I forgot where
I stole this one from but um this one is
a a nice one because I like that it has
our outcomes in it too
um with the learning theorists what
we're talking about here is kind of a
fun thing Skinner he's best known for
what's called Operate conditioning and
you may have heard about the little
Skinner box where the mouse run around
and they press these levels well what
he's trying to do is decide what
consequence um will determine if that
behavior happens again so if I push the
lever and I get food I'll be likely as a
mouse to go push that lever again to get
some more food so the consequences is
something that is um reinforcing I'm
going to keep doing it however if the
consequence is something that's
considered to be a punishment then I'm
going to decrease that behavior now what
we talk about when we talk about
reinforcement we're talking about both
positive and negative reinforcement now
here's where we have to come back to
some words the word positive and
negative this does not mean good and bad
if you went through our develop our iny
we push this and push this and push this
positive and negative refers to a number
line which side of zero are we on and
depending on what we're studying would
depend on which side you would like to
be on the word we want to focus here is
on the word
reinforcement anytime you see the word
reinforcement and I don't care which one
of these come in front of it remember
there's an increase in Behavior positive
reinforcement is talking about the
development of something good starting
negative reinforcement is talking about
something bad ending we don't like bad
things so we're going to make sure we
don't have those happen again and we're
going to find out whatever it is I need
to do to make sure it doesn't happen
again um the other thing he talks about
is punishment now we know something as
punishment if it actually decreases the
the chance that behavior is going to
happen again so if I touch a hot stove I
don't like it I'm not likely to touch
that hot stove
again now if you have not um taken our
our introduction to psychology class yet
or it's been a very long time there is a
lecture called conditioning and learning
that um I put together for psychology uh
1012 I'm going to put that in our class
you don't need to watch it unless you
really want to go back and sort of catch
up a little bit on conditioning and
learning it is something that they
assume that you know as you read through
this book because this course is
supposed to be taken after introduction
to psychology occasionally I get people
who get this before that so you might
really want to go and listen to that or
if it's been a very long time you may
want to choose to go back and listen to
that lecture it is not required
though now with the social learning
theorists what we're talking about is
observational learning or imitation and
we know especially with childhood this
is something that people are going to do
a great deal and you actually do this
even as adults because you think about
it you're going to be watching other
students you're going to be watching
other people in class do certain things
and then you're going to follow that
example so what we talk about
observational learning let's say that
you're in the nursing program and you
have to learn how to give a shot well
you know you're going to watch somebody
else give a shot first before you give a
shot I would hope so and so you're going
to be learning by watching other people
now what we do find is that imitation
tends to happen a lot more if we feel
like the subject is popular smar or
talented and that we think that there's
some sort of reward to that
behavior now with cogn development
theory we're talking about the
development of the thought process how
do we develop thought and there's going
to be a couple people we look at with
this now there are three basic
approaches that our book will talk about
P who looks at um stages so he kind of
thinks of this as being step by step by
step and then we got V here who really
says that it's
um not only the age but he thinks of
this as sort of an apprenticeship that
basically our social our culture is
going to influence a lot of how we think
about things and then last there's the
information processing Theory these are
more about computers and you know how we
bring information in and how we think
about it and the brain is really the
best computer out there now we as a
class don't really focus much on this
one if you are going into education you
may want to read up on this one a little
bit more but for most of our students
since they're going more into the uh
medical Fields it's just not one that we
bring forward a great
deal so let's look at P first well P
started to notice um this difference
when he was beginning to help people
develop a cognitive ability test um and
for France he was working with the banet
intelligence test and what he began to
realize is that you know kids and and
adults they they learned very
differently and so as he began to notice
that kids were learning differently he
wanted to know how that occurred well
what he began to realize is that kids
experimented they did little things if
we think about you know little babies
and we think about one-year-olds and
2-year-olds they're trying little things
doesn't matter how many times we tell
them something they're going to try it
anyway why is that because they have no
brains yet they're little squishy things
they're not mature brains like ours they
don't even have all the parts of the
brain yet um as far as thought cognitive
processes are concerned so P was very
interested in how does that develop over
time
so what he did is he focused on
development now the reason this is
important is he's not focusing on how we
learn he's not focusing on what we learn
he's focusing on the development how
does the brain develop over time and
then that development of the brain how
does that reflect on our cognitive
thought so don't confuse this with
education now cognitive stages he
believed um was because as children
became more
aware of their surroundings they became
increasingly more cognitive and one of
the things that's interesting about p is
that he came up with a lot of his
Concepts before we really even
understood the development of the brain
so he's a pretty smart
man now he also believed that there are
these three basic parts now we're going
to go into these again um when we start
covering I think it's chapter four or so
but this is just sort of a quick um
overview for you but he thought of these
three basic parts to devel the cognitive
development of the brain the first of
these schemas and what schema is is
basically a scene in your head and this
is how we think things are organized
This Is How We Believe something is
going to work and as we get older we are
going to course develop more of these
because we have more scenarios in our
head and so if we think about it when
I'm a kid all I think about is that
there's a car and it rolls down the Road
as I get older I begin to understand
that cars have parts and then as I get
older to that I begin that Parts Begin
to Fall Apart then I begin to understand
that there may have to be oil changes
and his question was is well how do we
begin to understand all that and so what
he said is that we have to adapt so an
adjustment has to be done and there are
kind of three parts to this adjustment
there's a simulation accommodation and
equilibrium now with a simulation what
we're doing is we're using our current
knowledge to understand the new object
situation so I'm a little kid I
understand that cars roll down the road
somebody gives me a little play car and
I roll it back and forth because I
understand that that's what cars do now
all of a sudden um I begin to understand
that cars have Motors and Motors run now
somebody gives me a toy car and I begin
to see if I can open the hood of that
toy car and I'm wondering why why can't
I open the hood to this toy car I don't
get this well what happens is our new
information doesn't fit our current
schema which is that cars have engines
and you should be able to open up the
car and see the engine well this is
going to get me frustrated from a kid
because this car hood doesn't open this
toy car and so I have to begin to
understand something and what I begin to
understand is that there's a difference
between the toy car and a real car once
I've got that some learning has happened
and my frustration goes away because I
understand toy cars don't have engines
and real cars do
now he believed that there were four
basic stages and again this is a very
very simple overview because we're going
to go into detail as we get through the
chapters the first one the sensory motor
is from birth to two years of age and
basically you know a little baby to two
years there's not a whole lot of brain
power going on yet he's basically or
she's basically just getting a concept
about the world although we're still
going through those stages we just
talked about we have a belief of what
happens and then things change and
that's where we get the learning
pre-operational stage we begin to get
the ability to use symbols and if we
think about it letters are symbols and
so why is this important because once we
begin to understand that letters are
symbols and once we understand what
symbols mean we can really begin to
develop language the other big thing
about the the 2 to seven year-old age is
that we only look at things based on our
own perspect our own perspective so this
egocentric istic kind of atmosphere
becomes and we've all heard the joke
about the 2-year-old the world is all
about me everything's about me and we'll
explore that further as we get into
other
chapters from there he thinks of us
having this concrete operational thought
that's seven to early adolescence
somewhere in there we're going to do
that what's going to begin to happen is
that we're going to use what we call
Here and Now logic you know this is what
I see so this is what it must be um
things are very concrete very black and
white during this phase and that's how I
kind of remember it it's the black and
white phrase you know pizzas only have
eight slices and so when you tell them
you're getting a pizza with 10 slices
they'll argue with you that you can't
have a pizza that has 10 slices or they
argue with you that you can't have a
pizza that's Square because pizzas are
always round things are very concrete to
them it's not until we get a little bit
older um sort of Beyond adolescence very
late high school early college that we
begin to develop this formal operation
and the big thing here is that we begin
to develop abstract thought
and we can begin to develop hypothetical
situations so hypothetically if this
happens what would happen hypothetically
if this would happen What would happen
and this is really a big developmental
stage according to P now P sort of ends
there but we're going to find out that
we keep developing thought after
that now Mr V here he's kind of
interesting because as I said he
emphasizes this social cultural
influence of Child Development where p
is only talking about development and
then learning this one's looking at how
our social learning influences our
development so one of the big things he
talks about is mkos or more knowledge of
others and what he believed is is that
we would learn best when we're in
situations that somebody knows something
just a little bit higher than me now the
person who knows that higher knowledge
doesn't have to always be much older
than me simply they know a little bit
more so what's going to happen is is
you're going to have a teacher and in
this case my teacher knows more letters
than I do so my teacher's going to help
me understand letters but I could also
be learning from a six-year-old who
knows more about letters than I do at 4
he really didn't focus on the age as
much as the fact that somebody would
know a little bit more than you that led
him to something called the zone of
proximal development and this is one
that again a lot of our medical people
uh people in our occupational therapy
assistant programs things in our nursing
programs people in our Health Service
Administration program we'll talk a lot
about zone of proximal development or
the zbd what we're talking about is what
is the difference between what I cannot
do without help versus what I can do by
myself now what we mean by this is that
you know if I I can't do it even with
help means that I do have the potential
to be able to do it so I can't sit there
and say well we're going to talk about
somebody who um oh let me give an
example somebody who's just had their
legs unfortunately amputated they don't
have their artificial legs yet so we
can't even talk about them walking yet
because I don't have their artificial
legs yet but now they get their
artificial legs so they still can't walk
but they could if somebody lifts them
and helps them and shows them sort of
that stepbystep stuff now the differen
is is what I can do by myself well I can
put my legs on by myself and I can learn
to stand by myself so the zone of
development is sort of learning to walk
we could walk with help we can put on
our legs by ourselves so what we're
going to be working with that patient is
this zone of development now we also
talked about doing this in school we
talked about this as adults but
basically this is what these kind of
Concepts were and again we're going to
go into these in depths as we get
through chapters that focus on those
areas remember this chapter is just
giving you a little overview a little
touch a little taste of each one of
these so you some basic knowledge going
forward now the epical sort of approach
Ro looks at Psychology very different
what they do is they say that all human
development is interactive and that we
can't just take one area of of
development and stick it off all by
itself that we're connected but that
there's no single thing to really de to
talk about development that um all
aspects of Our Lives sort of focus
within development this is one of our
newer areas of thought as far as human
development is concerned
because it really needed to have all
these other things that we've talked
about to sort of come together and what
the big person that we really talk about
in this one is
Yuri Yuri looks at this chart right here
and and you'll find this in your
textbook and I'm going to just tell you
right now you get to memorize and
regurgitate this uh there are test
questions on this but basically what he
says is that we have these different
systems and these systems are constantly
interacting with each other if you think
about it parent and child are always
interacting they're learning and
teaching to each other but I'm going to
use the example of music and we I'm
going to use Music um in Bard County to
show how these different systems come
together so if you look at the next
system out here the meso system you'll
notice that school is listed there well
the question is is how does music in
school reflect on the child well let's
say that you go to school here in Bard
County for you know 1 through sixth
grade well one of the interesting things
about that is that almost all of our
schools here in Bard County have some
sort of a music program with instruments
that is part of our schools now why do
they have that well let's go to the exo
system and over here we're talk about
government and policies well why we have
that is because we had a gentleman who
was the head of Bard County schools at
one point who truly believed that music
education was extremely important in the
development of a child's brain he truly
believed
that having spent the money on music
education that that would help develop
better thinking people well how does he
get that concept well he gets that
concept through historical events and in
this case it's through research studies
that show how music helps develop the
young brain so because of this
historical stuff out here the macro
system it it helped a government
official decide to dedicate money to
music systems and so musical education
became part of our school system and so
now if a child is in school first
through uh sixth grade they will have an
opportunity to learn a musical
instrument so that is where the child
will come home and say to the parent I
would like to learn violin and the
parent goes okay you know you're
learning violin at school that sounds
good that's a wonderful thing so it is
the these different systems that are
interrelated that winds up with this
child learning a musical instrument when
you perhaps have parents who never
played a musical instrument at all now
the other reason I bring music as a
great example is we think about Bard
County because in Bard County we happen
to have some extraordinary music
programs you would think all schools
have this music program but they don't
so it's because we had this government
official who decided that music was
important in our system that we have
early music education so how does that
begin to affect again the child in the
long run well there is this thing called
All State Orchestra competition and to
compete an all state Orchestra
competition this starts in seventh grade
all the musicians around the state play
the same piece of music and they select
the top players from the state to go to
the all state music orchestra now if we
talk about something like violin uh or
even the orchestra as a whole the
orchestra might have uh 50 kids in it
let's say only so many kids are going to
come from each County and you know to go
to all state to be the best among the 50
kids in the whole state to play a
musical instrument is enormous well with
violin out of the 50 players there might
be
20 25 oh it's actually even number 26
violin players let's say well what
happened one year is it's kind of a big
deal is that Bard County sent three
people to the junior high all state
music orchestra we sent three
violinists you might say well three out
of 25 well yeah except for the fact that
Miami Dade only sent one so if you think
about how large Miami Dade County is
that's you know the city of Miami and
they only had one person who could make
it and then you look at little Bard
County Which is far smaller but we had
three musicians who made it to the top
orchestra that shows you the Influence
of Music within the schools and that all
started from here from a government
official who decided that music was
important because he read it about some
historical events which then got into
the schools the schools liked it pushed
it down to the child and the parents
supported it and that's how this works
and that's what Yuri was talking about
that we can't just look at this as a
single event but that it's
interchangeable and that these different
layers work upon each
other now we are talking about the
lifespan approach and there are four
features that we're going to be talking
about as we go through our different
chapters one is called multi-directional
and that's basically that um the
development growth and decline sort of
happen at the same time you know we're
talking about maybe bones going up and
mental processing going down or this
moving this way and that one moving that
way we can't say everything is moving at
the same direction at one time so we
talk about multidirectional as far as
development is concerned plasticity
basically says that we can improve and
develop throughout our lifetime certain
skills and abilities we talk about the
plasticity of the brain a lot if you
think about that they can compensate the
brain learns how to compensate for this
or learns how to compensate for that but
plasticity basically is just saying that
we can improve throughout our lifetime
and most things we do we talk about
historical context we're talking about
how we must consider and examine
development over a period of time you
know what was the child like at 6 months
what were they like at a year what were
they like at 18 months and so historical
context caught often can tell us a lot
about development in the future so as an
example um my child did not get his
first tooth until he was 13 months old
now I know this because we kept joking
for his first birthday all the child
wanted was a tooth one tooth that's it
well he develops his first tooth at 13
months old so by knowing this now that
he is a much older child we realize that
all of his teeth are going to come in a
little bit later where other kids might
have these mullers and these other
things when they're young my child's not
going to be getting them until much
later because he's just simply
developing his teeth a little bit later
so a historical context in this case
gives us an idea of what's going to
happen in the future and what should be
happening here in the present so
let's say that most kids develop their
wisdom teeth around 15 we're guessing my
kid won't develop his wisdom teeth until
maybe 16 or 17 and so we're not going to
be too worried about that because we
know that simply as far as teeth are
concerned he's a little bit late on
teeth development not a big deal
probably something genetic within the
family
context multiple causation basically
says that there is not one thing to
consider again that's sort of like
multi-directional that different things
are growing different times so multiple
ation says that that something is caused
not just simply by a life cycle force or
simply by a biological but that we need
to look at all three and four things at
one time that it could be a
physiological a social cultural a life
cycle all happening and that all these
things together sort of help us
understand the development and so as we
talk about this lifespan approach we're
going to be looking at all four of those
now what's really interesting is is that
once we get into talking about sort of
kids and adults and all that our
chapters are actually going to be
divided up the first chapter is always
going to be biological and psychological
and the second chapters tend to be
social cultural and life cycle so
adolesence will go over two chapters um
you know school goes over two chapters
late adulthood goes over two chapters
and we have sort of this pattern that
begins to
emerge now when we start talking about
research the other thing that we need to
understand is that there's more than one
research project again we went through
this in introduction to psychology if
you did not get introduction to
psychology yet I'm going to encourage
you to listen to the chapter one um
video that I have posted from
introduction of psychology because it
goes into more detail about research and
developmental aspects of research again
they assume that you know this
information because you've had that
class or if it's been a really long time
since you've had that class you might
want to just go back and relisten to
that lecture just so you sort of catch
up and have this knowledge but the first
thing that they talk about in your book
is the systematic approach and when we
talk about that we talk about two basic
types of systematics approach first
would be like the naturalistic
observation real life so that's Jane
good all in the day and there's her
little chimpanzee I guess not really her
chimpanzee it's the chimpanzee out in
the wild and basically all I can do is
watch them I can't interact I can't do
anything with them I simply watch how
things happen in the real world and we
know how people say things happen versus
how things really happen can quite often
be very different so we don't want to
interfere in any way into What's
Happening Now jeane Goodall is probably
our most famous example of this but I
use this a lot in um consumer psychology
and we'll talk a little bit more about
that in class structured observation
basically says that I'm going to give
some sort of scenario I'm going to do
something and what I'd like to see is
what happens after that so I give you
something and I want to see how people
interact and how people work together
and we'd like to see how that changes
Behavior so I'm going to observe but I'm
going to give a little structure to that
observation we also have what we call
sampling behaviors and so what we may do
is we give you a task and we look to see
what you do with that task so in this
case we're asking about a kid to measure
emotional reactions which is a happy
phase which is a sad face we have
self-reporting and you've probably done
this at some point where somebody has
sent you a survey and they say would you
please you know tell us how you felt
today eating food and you filled out the
survey it's not a bad thing the problem
with self-reporting is how accurate are
you and again we may not be as accurate
as we think we do a lot of psychological
uh physiological measuring in Psychology
for psychological Concepts and a lot of
what we may do is be measuring brain
wave activities we may be measuring
pupil dilation because here we can see
physiological reactions to development
and to other
processes now we're going to be talking
about reliability and validity now these
are two words I want you to get into
your head pretty well reliability says
are we basically going to be getting the
same scores each time I mean a test
isn't very reliable if I take it one
time and I get one score and I take
another time get another score so think
about something like the SATs you know
if you take it and one time you get a
500 and the next time you get a 000 and
then you go back to 600 you how reliable
is that score and so we talk about you
know this is not reliable right here
we're all over the place now this one is
reliable because look at that we've got
four little spots right here together
but we're going to say it's not valid
why because we want the middle of this
so validity says am I actually measuring
what I say I'm measuring am I studying
what I want to say so over here we have
something that that's valid you know we
we are hitting all the target that's no
question about that but we're not real
reliable because again we're all over
the place so what we look for in
evaluating research methods is something
that's both reliable and valid basically
we're going to be hitting the middle
we're going to be close together in
those scores there's not going to be
much difference and it's going to be on
target meaning is that it's going to be
talking about the things we want it to
talk about so if we want to study how
smart somebody is giving them um a race
to run to see how fast they can do it
that wouldn't be very valid to determine
how smart they were that determines how
fast they can run and yes maybe every
day they can run this race and they get
basically the same score so the score is
reliable but it isn't valid and then we
could do something as I said with the
SATs where we're getting all these
different scores and we're like hey this
isn't very reliable because we keep
getting different scores but it could be
valid because it is measuring at that
moment in
time what your ability to do something
is we want tests that do
both we also need to make sure we
understand what a population is versus a
sample you know population is a large
group of people a sample may be a subset
of people so in this case pregnant women
um that represent the population now we
can't go and find every pregnant woman
and tester so we're going to use a small
percentage of those pregnant women and
then we're going to generalize out to
the entire population based on
that sampling that we
got now we also going to talk about that
there are different types of research
developments and this is a big one a
correlation now the big saying is that a
correlation does not prove causation it
shows relationships so it measures how
people score in two different variables
and basically what we're going to be
doing is looking at how two things
affect each other again if you haven't
heard this before you may want to go
back and listen to to that lecture I
have from chapter one from introduction
psychology we really kind of cover
correlations in depth there what we
bring into this one now that you
understand a little bit about
correlations is the fact that we're not
going to make those scattergrams every
single time because scattergrams after a
while they get a little hard to really
understand what's going on so we're
going to be doing something called a
correlation coefficient now this is not
a statistics class so you don't have to
calculate a correlation coefficient but
you need to understand what the little R
means now little r is basically the
symbol for correlation coefficient and
it can range between a negative 1 and a
positive one it can never be smaller
than negative 1 it can never be larger
than positive one why here's a positive
one notice that these dots are in a
perfect line and basically we make a
line straight through it it can't get
any more perfect than that and a perfect
negative one is just basically going the
opposite direction so we can't get any
more perfect than that this one in the
middle an R would equal to zero because
there is no gathering at all there's no
commonality to these at all there's no
relationship we would say now what we do
have down here is an example of a um an
R that's a positive six and an R that's
a negative six again let's not assume
that positive negative means good and
bad it simply means the left or right is
zero so in this case notice that the
dots are a little bit further apart and
that means that there's maybe not as a
closer relationship here as as there is
here this relationship is dead on if one
thing moves a quar of an inch the next
one's going to move a quarter of an inch
so a great one to use for something like
this is to show something like um
Fahrenheit and Celsius if something
measures in Fahrenheit and it goes up
you know two degrees it's going to go up
2 degrees and Celsius those things are
closely related down here we have the
same thing here we have two things that
are related but not exactly related um
but pretty close so in this case it
might be uh how much we watch TV versus
um our grades we would expect the more
TV we watch the further down our grades
would get but we might also want to
relink this to medication maybe if we
take a certain amount of medication we
actually see the number of symptoms
going down so in that case we'd like to
see a negative correlation between
symptoms and medication meaning is is we
want to see symptoms go down as we take
um more medication so remember negative
doesn't always mean a bad thing
psychology now with experimental design
we are talking about a cause and effect
relationship this is the only study that
gives us cause and effect between two
variables if I do this one thing what
will be the effect of that so we talked
about the fact that there were
independent dependent and extraneous
variables now your book basically just
talks about independent variables and
independent variables because again they
assume you understand what extraneous
variables are so remember that
independent VAR variable is the thing
that we manipulate it's the thing that
we expose to the condition whereas the
dependent variable is the outcome
there's always a number with a dependent
variable and that's how you always can
find it the question that we're always
trying to ask is does the independent
variable affect the dependent variable
and if so how much does it affect it so
as an example let's say that um I would
like to study the effect of calories on
weight loss so what I'm going to do is
have one subject eat 2,000 calories
another subject eat, 1500 calories and
maybe another one eat um 1,000 calories
and that is my independent variable is
that the number of calories we consume
will be different from person to person
and they do this for two weeks and at
the end of two weeks I then measure
their weight the score they get on the
weight is the dependent variable so
let's say one actually gains a pound the
first one who ate 2,000 calories the
person who ate 1500 calories they don't
lose anything they're the exact same
weight they were the person who ate
1,000 calories they actually lose 2
pounds so the independent variable did
affect the outcome it did affect the
dependent variable and that's basically
what experimental design is always
trying to
do another type of design we have is
called longitudinal studies and
basically what a longitudinal study is
is that we're going to study you over a
period of time maybe not over your whole
lifetime like this but what we'd like to
do is find out if something um changes
throughout your lifetime our biggest
problem with longitudinal studies is
that they are very expensive and very
timeconsuming think about this if I want
to study from birth to 10 years of age
it's going to take me 10 years to do
this study and meanwhile lots of things
could have changed U we also have a
problem because people tend to drop out
of longitudinal studies so over the long
period of Time how many people will drop
away from that study now with medicine
we do a lot of longitudinal studies
because we can begin to study how what
is the effect of medicine over a given
period of time so you could do something
like a diabetic who's going to be taking
insulin pretty much for the rest of
their lives depending on which type of
diabetic they are and there we can look
at development over a period of time the
problem with again longitudinal studies
though is that they're expensive they're
very timec consuming and we may lose
people
so to fix that we have something called
cross-sectional studies now a
cross-sectional study what we're going
to do is take a whole bunch of subjects
at the same time and we're going to be
dividing them up and looking at some
specific aspect so in this case what we
have is subjects from a population so
let's just say that these are all
um
oh we're going to look at people who are
18 years of age and we're going to look
at people who are 30 years of age and
what we're going to be be looking at is
lung cancer and so we're going to look
at people are 18 who smoke and versus
people who don't smoke so we're going to
take this one group of 18s and we're
going to look at the risk factor in the
disease and then we're going to take
30-year-olds and we're look at the risk
factor in the disease and we do this all
on the same day so what we're assuming
is that the difference between the
person at 18 and their lungs if they're
smokers and 30 if they continue to smoke
that whatever ever um whatever happened
is going to have happened because of the
time that was there so cross-sectional
studies are much cheaper we can do them
at one point but we do have the problem
that they are different people so why
one person seems to smoke all their
lives and not develop lung cancer and
another person smokes for a little time
and develops lung cancer that's not
going to be answered we're making some
generalizations but again we can't
always wait 10 years to get an answer to
a study but at the same point our
problem with this one is that we have
different people we're looking at we're
making the assumption that this
18-year-old is going to be equal to this
different
30-year-old to solve that we have
sequential studies and basically what
we're going to have is a series of
studies that are going to be done over a
period of time where we're doing both
cross-sectional and longitudinal studies
at the same time and so this sort of
gives you a chart of how complex a study
like this is now the word cohort we tend
to use that a lot here in Psychology and
people don't always know what that is
aort is a group of people of something
that is related so you hear the word
baby boomer all the time you hear the
word Generation Y Millennium babies the
xers those are cords there's something
that connects them all together in this
case it would be
age so what we have here is in um we're
going to be looking at the year birth so
people were born in 1994 versus people
born in 19 uh
96 and what we're going to do in the
year 2000 is that we're going to look at
six-year-olds and we're going to look at
8-year-olds and we're going to be
comparing them so this is the
cross-sectional right here because we're
talking about six and eight that's a
two-year difference but then we're going
to come back two years later and we're
going to look at 8-year-old and 10year
olds and again here we're doing
basically cross-sectional because we're
doing two ages but we can also now look
at how did the
8-year-old um here versus the 8-year-old
here is there any difference and that
would have happened because the
six-year-old grew up by two years and
that's the longitudinal sort of study
and then we're going to do the same
thing here when they're 10 and 12 now
that means is that we've been able to do
this study now in far less time we're
able to do it in four years but we got a
lot of information so we hope that
usually in sequential designs that we're
going to be able to get the same
information that might have taken us 10
years to do by doing it in this type of
format and yet we're still going to be
able the same people to be able to
measure the differ when they're 8 and 10
and 10 and 12 um to get that
longitudinal it is a lot more expensive
but most people really feel that this is
sort of the best design when we're
talking about development over
time now another one that's become much
more popular is a meta analysis and I
bring meta analysis in because I see
this a lot happening again in medicine
and we have a lot of our students who
are going to the medical programs and as
you read things they say this meta
analysis decid this and The Meta
analysis decided that so what's a
metaanalysis well here's an example of
an actual meta analysis right here and
we're looking at um a bunch of different
studies and that's what a metaanalysis
is we're going to take multiple studies
and we're going to Crunch all their data
together now we couldn't really do
metaanalysis until recently because we
just didn't really have the computers
who could do that now we have these
computers that can really crunch these
datas together so here you can be
looking at here's you know one study the
green is a different study each one of
these colors are sort of different
studies and we can begin to see if these
variables are repeated over time and we
can begin to see sort of a a look that
happens across time with this but this
meta analysis has really been very good
because it helps us to really understand
um sort of a bigger picture of what's
going on now the problem with the meta
analysis is that we're only using
secondhand data we don't collect
anything new it's all based on Old
research so while meta analysis are
really nice we also have to remember
that this data is not
fresh lastly what we like to talk about
is the process of communicating our
results and basically since we are again
talking about mostly in the medical
Fields we're going to use what's called
a peerreview
process and what happens is is that here
a paper is going be written by somebody
so I've done some study I've now got
some information I'm going to write my
paper and I'm going to submit it to a
journal now remember we're not talking
about any old Journal here we're talking
about a peer-reviewed journal again if
you need to understand more about this
go back and listen to that lecture on
chapter one introduction to psychology
now what happens here is that that's
been submitted over here to the editor
they're then going to take that and
they're going to hand it out to a whole
bunch of people who are going to look at
that paper determine whether or not it's
good bad or different they're going to
review it for accuracy validity for
reliability procedures they're going to
make comments they're going to give that
back to the editor who's going to
perhaps give it back to the author and
the author may have to make some changes
and this process will keep going around
now the thing is is that we keep going
around in this until we feel that the
science is right when we feel the
science is right then and only then will
it get published in a peer-reviewed
journal now this becomes important
because when things are published in
peer-reviewed journals we tend to think
of them as being the best science at
least the most accurate science of the
time now it doesn't mean that it
has it won't change over time because we
learn things and we say oh here's the
information we had and this was the best
we knew at the time you know I I like to
joke about the dinosaurs we apparently
had the wrong dinosaur heads on many of
dinosaurs for a very long time and we
had to go switch the dinosaur head
um somewhere in the ' 880s or 90s they
figured that out and yet we used to
think that the tales dragged on the
ground the dinosaurs and now we know the
taals probably were up and above the
ground um I always wondered about that
dragon on the ground wouldn't it scrape
it up but you know we now know it's
actually up and they were walking so
things do change over time but
peer-review journals are important
because when something comes out in a
peer rreview Journal we tend to feel
like it was the best science at that
time and that it wasn't just somebody
guessing so this isn't going to come out
in Time magazine or USA Today this is
going to come out in something like the
Journal of American Medicine or Jama and
that's one of the ones that we hear a
lot so on the news quite often they'll
be reporting tomorrow in Jama they're
going to publish this blah blah blah
blah blah blah blah blah blah blah and
so what they're reporting on is some
information that has been received
tested and we now believe is
accurate well this sort of ends up our
first chapter here in developmental
psychology I will see see you in class
and have a good day